what's going on guys it's ellam
welcome welcome to amigo scout
in this video
you're going to learn pretty much
everything you need to know
about jay ability using spring boot 3
so about 3 weeks ago
we posted a crash course on spring security
and there was a lag with JD blue tees section
so we decided to re record the entire section
and actually make it so extensive
this crash course right here is about to you by alibu
and is the one that led the spring security
so go ahead and subscribe to this channel
show some love because it's gonna be bringing you
awesome content like this
from time to time
security is a must when
designing and building apis
and it's really important that you understand JWT
so that you can secure your apis before we crack on
literally just take one 2nd and smash that like button
also if you new to the channel subscribe
and if you haven't joined the
private Facebook group as LS discord
go ahead and join
because the community is growing
and we're waiting for you
so
without further ado
let's get off
I just want to say that
you can grab the entire source code
and the description of this video
so that if you have any issues
or you want to take
what you learn from discourse and then apply it within
your own API you can do so
feel free to on the repo and
yeah just just use the code as you intend
and if you have questions regarding J liberty
literally just ask on the community
and someone within the community
will be able to help you
before we start the implementation process
let me 1st explain to you how this
JWT validation mechanism works
the whole story starts when a customer and a client
send an HDTP request to our
backend system
which is running using spring boot container
running on an Apache dumpkat embedded server
so just a reminder for you
the 1st thing that gets executed within
a spring application is the filter
so anytime and each time you create a filter
just notice and remember
that it will be the
1st thing that gets executed within our application
so in this case
the 1st thing that will be executed is our
JWT authentication filter
and this is only a one spur quest filter
and has the role to validate and check everything
regarding the token or the JWT token that we have
so now let's start the process
the 1st thing that will happen
we will have here
an internal check
to check if we have the JWT token or not
so if the token is missing
as we can see here
we will send a 403 response to the client
so and the reason is this missing JWT
right so now we have our GWT token and then
after that we will start the
process or the validation process
so this validation process will start in this way
so the filter like the internal execution
will 1st make a call using the user details service
to try to fetch the user information from the database
and this we will base on the user email
that we will set as a claim or
a token subject
that we will extract
within this JWT autontication filter
so I repeat again
this JWT autontication filter will check the JWT token
extract the username or the email
or we call it the subject
when we talk about JWT tokens
and it will use that email to fetch the user details
information from our database
okay so this is the 1st goal
then once the user
is fetched we have the response from our database
and the response can be either way
can be an existing user or non existing user
okay so once we get the response to our
JWT automatication filter
here we will make a few checks
which is if the user does not exist
we will also send 403
to our customer
in case everything is fine
and we get our user from the database
we will start then a validation process
so this validation process because
this JWT token was generated for specific user
so we want to validate this token based on the user
and here we have this validate JWT process or mechanism
which will try to call a JWT service
and this JWT service will take us parameter
the user itself
and also the token or the
string token or the JWT token
call it whatever you want
after the execution of this validation process
here we have to
case scenario
so the 1st one the token is not valid so it's not
so for example the token is expired or the token
is not for that specific user
so what do we do
we will send also a 403 back to our customer
so and the reason will be this unvalid JWT token
otherwise what will happen
we will
call or we will update the security context holder
and set this connected user
because when we fetch the user details information
from the database
we will be able to set
this security context holder
so we will tell spring
or we will tell
the set of the rest of our filter chain
that this user is now autonicated and we will update
the autontication manager
so every time we check if
this user is autonticated for this request
the answer will be yes
once the security context holder will be updated
it will automatically dispatch
the request
and it will be sent to the dispatch or servelet
and from the dispatcher serverlet it will be send
directly to the controller
we will do all the execution that we need to do
for example calling the service
going to the database and so on so forth
and then we will send back
a response
for example it can be a JWT and it will be an http 200
or whatever any
process that will get executed within this controller
so this is how JWT automatication mechanism works
now let me show you how to implement this
and how to realize these steps
let's 1st start by creating a new spring boot project
to do so
the recommended way and the way I also recommend
is going to start spring AU
which is the spring initializer
and create a new project from that
so 1st of all make sure you use maven
this is what I would be using in this
video antitorial
then we want to use the recent version of spring wood
which is now 301
okay and also here make sure you select java 17
because the minimum required version
which is compatible with spring 3
is java 17
next
select jar packaging
and now let's fill this project meta data
so for the group ID I will call it com dot alibu
and the artifact I will call it security
okay so I will leave the rest as it is
and now I will move on and add some dependencies
so 1st of all we need the spring web
because we want to expose few endpoints
we need also the security
and this is the main
object of this video
and then we will need
GPA or spring data
GPA because we need to manipulate
and interact with a database
then we need a post degree SQL
driver to connect to post degree SQL
you can also use any other
SQL database like my SQL or Oracle or whatever
finally we want to use longbook
to reduce the boiler plate code
so now we have our project ready
we can just go ahead click on generate and start coding
as I mentioned before we would be using post degree
s QL or as a database for this application
so let s 1st start by configuring our data source
for that I will be using
antilijay and they will use this database tool
so this one is available only with the ultimate version
otherwise if you don't have the ultimate version
just make sure you unstyle positive
SQL and you can use
the PG adamant
or you can use the debiver
tool to connect to any data source
okay so let's start with that
click on here and then we have this plus icon
so click on this plus icon
and then we want data source
and then filter for post degree SQL
click on that
and to be able to connect
so make sure here
if this is the 1st time you will have instead of driver
post degree SQL
you will have a link
or you will have a button here to download the driver
so just go ahead and click on it
and download the driver
next the host is local host because it's the local one
and the default port for post degree SQL SQL is 5432
then if you create when you created your possibly SQL
did you made or did you choose a username and password
if yes so just go ahead and specify them here
so for me
for the purpose of this tutorial I made it amigos code
and for the password it's just password
okay and then once you fill all this information
just to check if everything is working fine
click on this test connection
and make sure you get this succeeded
otherwise just check your configuration
alright so now everything is done
I will go ahead and click on OK
and the 1st thing that I will do is
I will create a new database
so
right click on this data source new and then database
so I will call it JWT security
and then hit okay
so the 1st time it will not be automatically shown
so just click here on this 2 of
8 the numbers may change from one laptop to another
and here I want this JWT security
okay so uh
open it in here
and here we can see that we have 0 of 3 schemas
just select the public one
because this is the one we need
and this is where we will find all our tables
once we create them
so now we have our data source available
let's move on to the next step
now let's
establish a connection between our application
and the database
we just created
so the 1st thing to do is
go here to these application properties
and rename it and use the representation yamal
okay so this is what I prefer personally
and you can keep properties if you want to
but to better follow this tutorial
it's better to transform a 2 yamal
so in order to connect to a database
we need to provide a bunch of properties right here
so we will start with spring
and then data source
and one
of the things that we need to provide at 1st is the URL
and this one is a URL
or the connection string to our database
if you don't know it just go here to this database
click on it right click on
the the connection you just created
properties and you copy this one
you copy this part right here
it's G d B C column post degree as create
and then the address port slash the database
so let me close this
I will base this one
and make sure here you
will write the correct database name
so for us we call the JWT security
now we need to provide the username and password
okay so for my case it's empty
make sure you provide the correct one
and here's password
so next property is
after providing
the data source information we want now to give some
other GPA properties
okay so here it will be GPA and then hibernate
and here I want to tell spring what to do
at the startup or up that application startup
and this property is the video auto
and here we have a bunch of
options so we have great drop create non update
and varied date
so I will be using the 1st one
because every time I want to start the application
I want to create a new database a news keyman
and when I stop the application I want to destroy it
okay so I always want to start with empty database
alright so the next one
within JPA within JPA
like you see now you need to
really pay attention about the antentation right here
because this one
the studio auto is part of the hibernate
and the one I will write right now is part of JPA
so it's spring JPA
and then show SQL
I want to show SQL
when when we perform or when
spring date and JPA performs um
equally I want to see that way
okay
I want also to add some other properties
so here I will add properties
and one of these properties
and here I have hibernate
and within this hibernate I want also to format the SQL
so format sq and through
I want my queries to be formatted
now go back to the same level as properties
and provide some information about the database
so here we want to tell GPA which database we are using
and for this case we are using post degree SQL
and then
we can also provide
the database platform that we are using
and this will help spring performing and writing the
better aquaries to to suit our postgrave and database
so for this one it's org hibernate
dot DIOLICT
dot post green esque and dialect
alright
and here we just forgot one property right here
which is the driver class name
so this will help
a spring to detect or use the best driver class name
and here we are using post degree SQL
so until a J will automatically propose it to you
otherwise it's the org post degree SQL driver
and this is the one that we got
from the post degree SQL driver
dependency
alright so that's it about this configuration
let's move on and start implementing our security
when we talk about authorization and authentication
we mainly talk about users
so let's go ahead and create our user class
so within the java package
and within the main package that we have right here
right click and
new class and here we can
create a package on a class at the same time
so the package I will call it user
and here I will just call the class user
so user to user will create a package user
and inside of it
it will create a class user
alright so this is our user class
let me make this one full screen
and now I want to write a bunch of properties within
this class okay
so my user has
the following characteristics or the following fields
so 1st of all I want to have an antiger ID
and then I want to have
a string 1st name
one private string last name
and also of course we need an email and password
for this user to be able
to authenticate and connect to our application
so here I will add email
and also private strength password
so these are the information about
our user now I will add a bunch of
lung book annotations
in order to reduce the boiler plate
because you know when we create
in class we need getters and setters
we need constructors
we need also
the design partner builder
to be able to easily build our object
and so forth so let's start with that
so we will need the date
annotation and this annotation will provide us with
is the equivalent of getter setter as you can see here
so it generates getters
for all fields
for useful methods to string and so on so forth
so it's the equivalent to the getter setter required
arts constructor to string and equals and hash coat
okay
also I want to use the builder annotation
so this builder annotation will help me
build my object
in an easy way using the design pattern builder
okay and also I will need the no arx constructor
and of course when we talk about design pattern builder
we need
always the all construct the or arx constructor
okay so let's add this one
and like this we
have our user class
now let's make this user class an entity
to make this user class and NTT
so the 1st thing we need to add is this NTT annotation
and since we are using the springwood 3.0 here
make sure that the package is
Jakarta dot persistence and it's no longer java eggs
persistence so this also will help you tell
if you are using the correct version of spring boot
okay so here we need the entity annotation
and because this username
this
user class is already reserved for postigrae esquell
because postegrae escale already has
a table called user
so we cannot create a 2nd table called user
I will use the table annotation right here
because you know the table annotation
if I do not provide
if I don't provide any
name right here
it will take
the entity or the class name as a default name for
the table okay
but here I want just to call it androscour user
to avoid this
ambiguity between this user class and the one with
and the one with post degree sq
so now this is
kind of sufficient to tell that this user
class now is an entity
but we still need to provide
one small information
okay so here we have this
error right here
we see that this persistence
entity user should have a primary key
okay so we need to add an at an ID attribute
which we already have right here
but we still missing this ID annotation
so this ID annotation is
coming from the jackart adult persistence
and it's telling that this ID is
the unique identifier of this user class
now I want also this ID to be
auto incremented or auto generated
so every time I want to create user
I don't need to provide this ID
and every time this ID is now
I wanted to be auto incremented by the system or by
spring data JPA itself
so to do so and to make it in an easy way
I will use a notation generated value
okay so this generated value
it will make this ID or this object auto generated
using whether a sequence a table and so on so forth
and we call this is strategy
so for this strategy
we have several options
OK we have auto identity sequence stable and
UYID
so
the auto is the default value
identity means that it will use
an identity number like an auto ancrement
sequence means that we will create a sequence
within our database
and use this sequence to
increment each time the value of the ID
the table this means that we will create a table
in the database and we will call it
by default it's called hibernate sequence
and this table will always be requested and queried by
spring data JPA
to get the last value and incremented for the last one
the UU ID is using this one I think you know it from
from the java java utils
but if you leave it to Otto
if you leave the generation type to Otto
hibernate
will try to detect the best suitable option for you
for example if we are using post degree s crel it will
by default sequence
if you are using my SQL for example
it will pick table
because my SQL does not work with sequences
so it will pick table for that
so for the moment I will just keep it empty
like this
because as I mentioned the default value is auto
so it will be automatically detected
okay so now we have our entity
let's try to start the application
and make sure that we have our table created
within the database
here enable the annotation processing for longbox
and now we have our
application started
let's have a look quickly on the logs
and here we see that create sequence
user sequence start with one increment by 50
this is automatically generated as I mentioned
and here we see the SQL that we have create table user
with an ID email and so on so forth
okay and here we have
spring security is auto generating a security password
and this one we will see later on
okay so also if you want to check
you can open your database right here
click on this one refresh it
and within the public schema
we see that we have this user table right here
and if we open it
we will see the ID or the attributes
attributes that we already provided
when spring security starts and set up the application
it will use an object called user details
and this user details is an interface
that contains a bunch of methods okay
and each time you want to work with spring security
you need to ensure
that you are providing these user details object
in order to make
spring security life easy to use
okay
so to do this for us for our user I recommend this way
so every time you have user think
always to make it
or to implement the user details interface
so like that your user or your application user
is already a spring user if we may say so
okay so to do that
just go ahead
to this user class that we created
and implement an interface called user details
okay and this user details is from the package or
spring framework security core user details
okay click here
and now it will ask us to implement a bench of method
so click on this one implement method
and we see right here
that these are the methods that we want
or that we need to
auto generate
okay
not autogenerate but we need to implement
so let's get authorities username
and we have this bullion
methods account expired locked and so and so forth
okay so just go ahead click OK
and we will see how to override
but before that I want to go a bit
more into details about these user details interface
so I will open the definition download the source
so we can easily see it
so here
if I click on this icon right here
to see all the implementation of
this interface
we have this mutable user
mutable user details and so and so forth
and also we have our user class the one that we created
and we can see also that we have this user
from spring framework security core user detailed
and let's have a look on this one
okay so
this user detail contains the username
password authorities and the bench of bullions
the account expired
locked non expired and enabled or not
and this information on this
this attribute spring will use automatically
to play with authorization and authentication
and for example
if we we can't really rely on this account non expired
where if we want to have some expiring
dates or use the user can expire
and also if we want to lock and unlock the user
or the same if we want to work with credentials
and so and so forth
okay so I will give you the time to play and check this
and here we see that we have a bunch of constructor
and we have these methods
that they need to be overridden right here
okay
so here we see that these user
already implements user details
so for you you have 2 options
whether
you implement this user details interface within
your user class
or you can create for example a user
you call it up user and then extend user
the one from springboot so it will be the same
but
for me I want always to have control over my object
so I create my own user class and
implement user details
so now let's go ahead and implement these methods
okay so here the 1st one is
we need to provide a collection of granted authorities
and already the method is called get authorities
so this get authorities
will return or should return a list of roles
like let me explain like that when we talk about roles
so here we need to add
role okay so I will do or I will create a role
and this one it will
I will create an in amp for it and I will call it roll
and this let's create this class
and here you can choose the option create an arm role
hit OK and we want to create it within the same package
and within this role
it's so easy I will just user
and admin okay so
we want to have only 2 roles within our application
so now we have this role and because it's an enam
we need to add this enumerated annotation
and this enimmerated annotation is to tell
spring that this is an enam
and we want to use it whether the enam type
ordinal or string
so by the way
by default its ordinal means it's 012
and so on so forth
string it will take the string value
of the inner okay
so let's go back to this again
authorities so in here
because
with our design
we said or we decided that user can have only one role
so I will just return a list
dot off
and here I want to return a new simple
granted authority
okay so the object that I want to return is called
simple granted authority
and here I want to return the role
name
okay so the role is refrancing this role right here
next one is this get user name so the user name for us
is our username so it's the email
okay
then we have this account not expired
so here we have this is account non expired here
make sure and be careful it's non expired false
this is the negation
so non expired should be true
otherwise we will not be able to connect our users
so non expired non locked and
non credential on expired
and if the user is enabled fault
and here I want to make it true here
there is one thing that I need to mention right here
so within
this method let's go back to this user details
interface we see that we have this get password
okay but this cat password
was not overridden right here
because we have this string
password right here
and we have the longbook annotation
so we have already the method called get password
but here if I just
name this one we see that we will see that here
we will automatically
tell that we want to override this method
okay so let's override it
just to be um
to be more visible or like better visible for you
I will rename this one to password
and here for this password I will just return my
my password okay
so I just wanted to mention this one
so in the next time
or like
when you have a different name for this password field
you don't get surprised when you see this get password
or when you have this password exactly
like that and you don't see it
so now you know the reason why
okay so now we have everything we need within our user
details so we created a new role
and we over written
or we defined all the methods that are required by
spring security
now our user is ready
so let's move on and create a repository for that
user class so the repository is the class
which is responsible to communicate with the database
so when working with spring data GPA
we don't need to create a class
all we need to do is create an interface
and let's call it user repository
and this use a repository to make it a repository
all we need to do is to extend
another interface called JPA repository
okay and as you can see here
this JPA repository is from spring framework data JPA
and so on so forth
and it's a generic interface that takes a t
so which is the class and an ID
which should be the ID of our user class
so let's use this one and pass these types
so this the user and we used antiger as an ID
so let's pass antiger right here
okay so now our repository is ready
and as you know the spring data JPA has also
a bench of methods or ready to use methods
like save find all find by ID and so on so forth
okay
now I will create one method that we will need later on
and this method
will try to retrieve or find a user by email
because email is unique
so we need to find or we need to fetch
a user by its email
alright so I'm going to create this optional
user and like optional is a generic type
so it's an optional of user
and here I will use the query method
provided by spring and I will use the method find by
and here all you need to do
is providing
the attribute or the field
name that you have within your class
so for our case its email
for example if you use username just find by username
and here all you need to do is to pass string email
alright so
this is it now we have our repository ready to use
let's move on to the next steps
when we check again our
schema right here
and the architecture that we have right here
so we see that the 1st thing that we will get
or the 1st thing that will intercept our http request
is the JWT orphantication filter
so let's go ahead and create this filter
so here within our base package right click right here
new
and I will create a new package I will call it config
so I want
all this to be part of my configuration package
and I will create a JWT authentication filter
I will call it like that
so this is our authentication filter class
and now in order to make it a filter
we have multiple options
okay but here
as we can see in the skima right here we have the
we want this filter to be
active every time we get a request
so every time the user sends a request
we want our filter to get fired and
do all the job that we want
that we wanted to do okay
so this one we need to extend
a class called one's per request filter
and as the name indicates it will be a filter by one
every request
so let me download the data source
and you can see here
a one spread quest filter
extend already generic filter bean
and this generic filter bean
already implements the interface called filter
so for us we had 2 options
whether using or extending
this one spare request filter
or implementing the filter interface right here
so it will be the same but let's use something
already provided by spring
so it's better to use the one's per request filter
so now let's implement the methods
and we see here that we have a method called do
filter internal
and we have 3 parameters
the request the response and the filter chain
let me explain each part of it
I will just in line these parameters right here
so you can see all of it
so these are our
parameters so here what we have we have this HDB
service request the response and the fitter chain
so the request is our request
and the response is also our response
so we can intercept
every request and make an extract data
for example from the request and
provide new data within the response
so for example if I want
to add a header to my response
we can do it using this one spread request filter
okay and the filter chain is the
chain of responsibility design pattern
so
it contains the list of the other filters that we need
we need to execute
so when we call this filter chain dot
do internal filter
or do filter
it will call the next filter within the chain
so here I want just remove this
these warnings so because
these 3 parameters they should not be null
and to do so I will just add this
non null
annotation the one from spring framework to tank
and I'm going to copy paste it and move it and put it
in here okay
so like this we no longer have this warning
and now the last thing to do
before moving on and start implementing this
the last thing to do is we need to tell
spring that we want
this class to be managed being
okay or to become a spring being
and to do so we need to annotate
whether with service annotation
or component annotation
or also repository
it works because 3 of them are the same annotation
the repository and the service
they both extend the component
but I will just make it a component right here
and also I will use another
long book annotation which is
the required arx constructor
and this required arx constructor
it will create a constructor using any
final field that we declare right here
so for example if I use
if I do private final string my string
this annotation it will create
a constructor using this private final field
okay so
now we have our
filter rated use
let s now start implementing it part by part
from this diagram right here
we see that the 1st thing that
gets executed
or the 1st thing we do within
this JWT authentication filter
is checking if we have the JWT token
okay so let's move on and implement this
alright to do so within our method do internal filter
let s try to perform some
operations okay
so 1st of all I will create a string
I will call it authonication header
alright why
because when we make a call
we need to pass the JWT authonication
token within the header
so it should be within a header called authorization
so what we need to do here is
try to extract this header
okay
so this authentication header is part of our request
and from the request we can call a method
called get header
and within the header we can
all we need to do is to pass the header name
so
our header is called authorization
like that
so this is the header that contains the JWT token
or the bureau token
we call it also bureau token
okay
alright so now I will create another variable
let's also make a final string
I recall it JWT or JWT token call it whatever you want
so here I want to implement this check that we did
before so
we talk about here we talk about this check JWT token
so let's go let's implement this
so here the test that I want to do is if
the authorization header is null
so I want to do an early return
or
if not my authorization header
starts with because as I told you the beer token
should be
always or should start always with the keyword beer
okay and it should be exactly like that
and then we have a space
so if we don't have these 2 conditions
all I need to do is call the filter chain dot
do filter and I need to pass the request
and the response to the next filter
okay and here don't forget to call the return
so we call in
so we want we don't want to continue with the
execution of the rest
of that one okay
so
here this is the check
that we implemented
now let's try to extract the token from this header
okay from this authontication header
the next step is we created already a JW team variable
now I want to extract this token from
my authentication header
or from my authorization header
and I want to do a sub string
starting from the position number 7
and why position number 7
because if we count this beer with this space
the count is 7
okay so let's move on and check what we need to do next
after checking the JWT token
what we need to do is to call this user detailed
service to check if we have the user
already within our database or not
okay but to do that we need to call a JWT service
here to extract the user name
alright so let me show you what we need to do
so right here
I will just go back and create a final string
username or email call it whatever you want
so I'm just gonna call it user email
okay to be consistent and avoid confusions
so I will call it user email
so after extracting the JWT token
what I need to do is I want to extract
also this user email
so these user email equals
and here I will add it to do extract
the user email
okay but to do so I need to extract it from
let me add it here from JWT token
so to extract this user email from the token
I need a class that can manipulate
this JWT token
okay so
let's try now to implement this class
this class I will call it here
I will just create my class here
private final I will call it JWT service
so I don't have yet this JWT service
but within this JWT service at what I want to do here
I want to use a method that I will call it for example
JWT extract username
okay so let me call this JWT service
dot
extract user name or user email
okay let's keep it username within the JWT
because mainly with spring security we talk about
user names
and to extract this one I need to pass the JWT
as a parameter
okay
so
I will create this class
now I will ask
until the J to create this class JWT service
and I will create it
you can keep it whether
with the config package
or you can move it to the front one
so I will keep it within this package
and also do not forget to add this service annotation
to make it or to transform it to a managed bean
alright
so now I will just create this extract username method
so create method extract username in JWT service
and yes this is what I want to do
I need a method that will
return a string username
and it takes as a parameter string token or string JWT
okay so let me call this one token
I think it would be better as a name
and yeah that's it
so I will just return now for the moment
and let's move on and they will show you how we can
how we can implement
or how we can extract this information from our
JWT service
so now in order to be able to manipulate JWT tokens
generating one
extracting information from the token
validating the token and so on so forth
we need to include
new dependencies within our application
so let's go open our palm XML file
and here within this palm XML
scroll down and go next to the long book
or post degree ascretel dependency
and here just add a new dependency
and this is the 1st one called JJWT API dash API
and it's from AIO just dot JSON web token
okay and the recent version at this time is the 0115
so let's use this one
we need also to add another dependency
which is also from the same artifact
from the same group ID but it's a different artifact
so we need a JJWT implementation
so it's called JJWT
and from the same group ID
also the same version you can extract this version to
a property and use it from there
and next we need a final dependency which is the JJWT
Jackson okay
so also from the same group ID and the same version too
now once we add
or once you add these dependencies
or any dependency to your palm XML
or if you make any updates to your palm XML
make sure you click this button
load maven project
but also if you don't see this button just right click
inside the bomb
XML file
maven and then you have the option reload project
okay so antilly J will download
all the dependencies and add them
to the class path
alright so our dependencies are ready to use
now we will go back and implement this JWT service
so before we go and implement
all the services and dive too much into the code
let's 1st try to
understand what is a JWT token
so a JWT token stands for a JSON web token
which is a compact URL safe
means of representing claims to be transferred
between 2 parties
the claims in JWT are encoded as JSON object
that is digitally signed using a JSON web signature
okay so the JWT consists of 3 parts
so here we have the header
we have the payload and also we have the signature
so the header typically consists of 2 parts
the 1st one is the type of the token which is JWT
and the sign in algorithm being used
such as for example HMAC or SH 256 or
RSA okay
the 2nd part of the token is the payload
which contains the claims
claims are statement about an entity typically the user
and additional data
so as we can see here we have the subject
we have the name
we have this IAT we have
we can have also extra information
like authorities or extra claims
right here okay
so
there are 3 types of claims registered
public and private claims
the registered
claim claims are a set of predefined claims
which are not mandatory but recommended
to provide a set of useful intropuable claims
some of the registered claims R is a R
ISS or the issuer
we also have the subject the OD
the X exb like the expiration time on so on
so far
this we will see when we
will implement the token generations
we have also the public claims
which are the claims that are defined within
the IA and ajson web token registry
or public by nature
private claims are
custom claims created
to share information between parties
that agree using them
okay
the last one
or the 3rd part of the token is the signature
which is used to verify the center of the JWT
is who it is claims to be
and to ensure
that the message wasn't changed along the way
okay so now let's move on to the code
and see how we can generate
or how we can
extract claims from this JWT token
okay so also within this JWT website
you can play with the payload
you can add some information here
and as you can see everything you add some
every time you add something
you see that it changes right here
okay let's move on and go back to our code
now before
start implementing this extract username method
I want to implement or write some code to extract
all the claimed and also another method to
that allow us to extract one single claim
okay so
1st of all I want to create this method
I will it will return acclaims
and these claims
if you see right here when you click on import class
it's the one from Io
jsonwebtoken claims
it's the dependency that we just added
so these claims I will call this method
extract all claims
okay so this extract or claims
of course it will take a string token asparampter
and now I will show you how to extract this
so to do it
we need to return
our JWTS and this JWTS is also from
so this JWTS is also from the Io dot JSON web token
and we need this JWTS dot pars builder
and in order to pass this builder or the
TOPAS the token
and here we need to set the signing key
okay set signing key
because as we mentioned before
when we try to create
to generate or to decode a token
we need to use the signing key
so I will hear just let coca this one
get signing key and I will explain it later on
we will implement this method
and then we need to build because it's a builder
and once the object is build
we can call the method pass claims JWS
okay so this one
this method pass claims JWS
so we want to pass our token
and once the token is passed
we can call the method get body
okay so within the get body we can
get all the claims that we have within this
this token right here
alright so now
now
before we implement this signing key method we should
return a key as you can see in the definition here
so this one
let's 1st understand what is a signing key
okay so in the context of chase on web tokens
a signing key is a secret that is used to digitally
sign the JWT
the signing key is used to create the signature
part of the JWT
which is used to verify that the sender of the JWT
is who it claims to be
and ensure that the message
wasn't changed along the way
so we want to ensure that the same person
or the same client
that is sending this JWT key
is the one that claims who to be
okay so
the signing key is used in conjunction with
the signing algorithm
specified in the JWT header to create the signature
the specific sign in algorithm
and key size would depend
on the security requirement of your application
and the level of trust
you have in the signing party
okay so
here in order to do that
1st of all we need to go ahead and generate a new
token or a new signing key or a secret secret key
so to generate this secret key we can do it online
because now
for security reasons we need at least or the minimum
a signing key of size 250
6 okay so
and in order to generate a key so
you don't need to worry about this
there are so many tools and online tools to do this
so here I will just go ahead and create a private
static final
string I will call that secret key
and this secret key equals the value that I will
generate right now
okay so now go to the browser
and navigate to this address which is all keys
generator com and then
random
security incorruption key generator a
SPX okay and we have here encryption keys
and here we have also the security level
so as I mentioned
the minimum required for JWT tokens is 256 pit
okay and then click on this checkbox
yes that the X
make it check it and make it yes
so we can get this X
X secret key okay
so if you need more security just go ahead
change it and do like
you can go even up to
496 bits okay but for now for the sake of this
tutorial I will just make it or leave it to
256 bit
okay now let's go back to our code and paste
this code right here or this key right here
also you can move it to the application properties
and use it from there
alright now let's continue
and let's implement this get signing key
so here I will use antiligate to auto
generate or to create this method
so I will ask how to create this method
and this method should return not bite
but it should return a key
okay so
now to do this
1st of all I need to create or to make an object
or variable of type byte
I will call it key byte
and this one equals decoders
and the dot
base 64
because it's a base we want to decode it on base 64
dot decode and we want to decode our secret key
okay so once the secret key is decoded now
I need to do just to return keys
dot
HMAC shah key 4
this is one of the algorithms that we mentioned before
and all I need to do is to pass these key bites
right so now we have our gate tiny key method
and we have also this
extract all claims method ready to use
now we have extract all claims method ready to use
I will go ahead next and implement another method
which will allow me
or which can extract
a single claim that we pass
okay so I will use generosity for this
so I will use a public t
I wanted to be a generic method
now they will call it extract claim
and for this claim I need of course the token
the key token or string token
and then I want to pass a function
the one from java utils
and this function is of type claims
and t which is the type that I want to return
okay I will call it claim resolver
or claims resolver or claim
call it whatever I want resolver
and here it's a it's a simple uh it's a simple method
I will create a final claims object
I will call it claims equals extract all claims
from my token
okay so 1st of all I want to extract all the claims
and then I want to do return
this claim a resolver
the function that I pass as parameter dot apply
and as you can see
the apply it will take or it will require a claims d
so the claims is the one
of the list of all the claims that we have
okay
so this is the extract all claims all claims method
now extracting any claim
from my token will be an easy pizzy task
so I will show you how to do that
so once I have everything ready
extracting all the claims and also extracting one
single claim
let me show you
how we can extract the username out of this token
okay so extracting a username is easy PZ
so it will be extract claim
and we need to pass the token
and only we need to pass the claims
dot get subject
okay so because as I mentioned before
the subject is
or should be the email or the username of
of my user
okay so this should be the subject of the token
so that's it
this is only all about extracting the username
let's now move on and try to implement other methods
that we will need within this JWT service class
like testing if the token is expired also
extracting the expiration date
generating the token and so on so forth
let s now implement the method that will
help us generate a token
so the token as you know is a string
so I will create a public
string method
and I will call it generate token
alright so this generate token
will take us parameter a map
a map of string and object
okay and this map of string object will
will contain the claims or the extra claims
that we want that we want to add
okay I will call it claims or like extra claims
I think it's better to call it extra
claims and also I want to pass my user details
so here user details
and it's the one from the spring framework
I will just call it user or user details
alright so this is the method and here
this extra claims is the one if I want for example
I don't know to pass authorities
to pass any information that I want to store within
my token right
so to do this it's easy easy it's just return JWTS
dot builder
and then I want to set
my claims
so this are my claims
and those will be the extra claims okay
so extra claims
and after passing the claims I need to set my subject
so the subject as I mentioned before
it should be my username or user email
okay so I will use the object user details
that get username
alright so because for us username or the unique
part of the user is the emaid
but for spring it's always called username
that's why we are using username
okay so also we need to set the issued art
means that when this claim was created
and this information will help us
to calculate the expiration date
or to check if the token is still valid or not
okay so I will use a new date right here
and I will pass just the system
dot current milliseconds okay
so this is
the issue the issue date
and it will also to set the expiration date
so the expiration date it will be the same new date
and here like it's up to you to set how long
this token should be valid
okay so also system dot
get dot current milliseconds
and then for example I want to add
let's say 1000
times 60 which is 60 minutes times to 24
so my token for example will be will be valid for
24 hours plus 1000 milliseconds
okay and then you can
you can decide
or you can set any expiration date that suits you
okay
the final step is to sign with
like which key that we want to use to sign this token
and the signing key
is the get signing key method that we
already created before
and then we need to pass also the signature algorita
so signature algorithm and then we want to use the
HS256 okay so to this one
so let's select it and then
finally call the method compact
compact is the one that will generate and return
the token so as you can see
this is how we can generate a token out of
extra claims and the user details
all right so
now this method will
like we don't have a choice
but passing claims and user details
but what if I want to pass or I want to use
or I want to generate a token
without having or without extra claims
I only I only want
to generate a token from the user details itself
so it's easy busy I will create
another one
public string
I'll give it the same name generate token
and the generate token it will take it
I will pass only user details
as a parameter
and here I will just return generate token
out of null or let's say
a new hash map like an empty one
and then user details
okay so now I have this generate token method
that I can use
later on okay
as a next step let s implement a method that
will validate or can validate a token
okay so
are we create a bullion
and I will call it is token valid
alright and
this method is token valid
will take 2 parameters as
input which is the token itself
and the user details
why we need user details
because we want to validate if this
token right here
belongs to these user details right here
okay so 1st of all I need a final
string username or user email
but within this within the context of this JWT service
let's stick to username
and this one it would be
extract username out of the token
we already have the method for that
and then then what we want to do is to return
if or whether the username that we have right here
equals
the user detains dot
get username alright
so we want to make sure that the username
we have within the token
is the same as the username we have as input
okay and I want to make sure is is token expired
like I need to check that my token is not expired
okay and I want to pass my token as parameter
so this is token expired
this method that we need to create
so let me go ahead and create this token expired
and let's implement this token
okay so
I want for this is token expired I want
I will create a method
I would call it extract expiration
from the token that we have
dot before because it's a date
so I want to make sure that it's before
today's date okay
before new date
now let's create this extract expiration
so this extract expiration should return a date
and it has or it passes as a parameter
the token itself so it's also easy
so it's extract claim from the token
and then it claims
or colon colon get expiration
okay so this is how we can extract the expiration date
alright so we have here if
the east token expired we have the east token valid
we have all the methods that we need
so is to converted this one we'll use it later on
so now let's move on and go back
finish implementing this
authontication filter
so here we just finished implementing this
JWT validation process or validation service
right here
and now we want to go back to this validate JWT process
so within our code
what we did here we extracted our username
so we have now our username valid
let's go ahead and perform or finish
our validation process
alright so here I want to check if my user email
is not null
so I have user email or I can extract my user email out
of my JWT token
and I want to check something else
I want to check that the user is not authenticated yet
because if the user is authenticated
I don't need to perform again
all the checks and setting or and updating
the security context and so on so forth
so here I want to check if the user is
already authenticated
I don't need to do all this process and so on so forth
all I need to do is pass here and
leave it to the dispatcher servelet
okay so
to do that or to check if the user is
already connected or is
already authenticated or not
we have an object called security context holder
and from that we can get the context
and then we have a method called get authentication
and when the authentication is
now means that the user is not yet authenticated
okay so this means that the user is not connected yet
alright so once the user is not connected
what we need to do here
like when we go back to follow this process
we need to perform
and to check or get the user from the database
alright so once we do this validation process we want
also or we need to
check if we have the user within the database
alright
so to do so I will create an object called user details
or you can just call it user
because our user already
extends or implements the user details interface
I will call it user details equals
and here I will use this dot user
details service which we don't have yet
and here we have a method load by user username
okay
and you and my username in this case is the user email
alright
so here the method called load user by username
and in this case we don't have this user detailed
service but let's create one here
so this user detailed service is already an interface
within the spring
available within the spring framework
and it's from
spring framework security core and so on so forth
and I will call it user details service
so this interface if we check it right here
so here we have some implementation for it
okay but we want our own implementation
because we want to fetch our user from our database
alright so make this one final don't forget this
and let's move on
and implement or provide a bean of type user details
service
at this level
we need to create a beam of type user details service
or we need to create a class that implements this
interface so
and also give it the service or component annotation
so it becomes a managed bean
and spring will be able to inject it
but let's do it in a fancy way
within this config package I will create a class
I will call it application config
so this application config
will hold all the application configurations
such as beans and so on so forth
alright so to make this class a configuration
we need to unnotated
with the annotation called configuration
so at the startup spring will pick up this class
and try to implement and inject
all the beans that will declare within
this application config
alright we also need the
required artist constructor in case we want to inject
something
so what we need to do now
is to implement or to create a beam
of type user details service
and to do so
1st of all we need to use the annotation bean
this to indicate
to spring that this method represents a bean
and a bean always should be public no private beans
and our being is of type user details
service okay
so
let's call it the user details service
as easy as that or as simple as that
and then
we can use alumnida expression
so we can use
or we can say return a new user detailed service
and we implement the load
user by username
so we can do like that
new user details service
like this and automatically
you'll see here that we have this
load user by username method the one that we
want to use in here
this method right here
okay but
but we can make it more simple than that
and we can use a lambda expression
and the lambda expression it's
it looks like that so here we already see that
antilly J is proposing to replace this with a lambda
so we'll just go ahead and click on it
so the lambda is the username
so we provide the username the one we have as an input
within this method right here
and then we need to provide the implementation
okay so
in this case what we want to do is
to fetch
the user or to to get the user from the database
and to do that we need to inject our user repository
okay so let's create a private final user repository
let's call it a repository or user repository
and here
simply what we need to return is user repository
dot find by email the method that we created
when we just created the
user repository
and find by email we need to pass the user name
okay
and since the find by email returns an optional of user
here I want to add an RL's throw
so in case we don't have or we don't find
the user name or the user within our database
we need to return an exception of type
whether entity notefound exception
or we can also return
the exception username notefound exception
okay so I will use the username not found exception
and I will
just provide here it should be also alarmed up
and for example as a message we can say user not found
alright so here now we have our user details service
so now it's ready to use
let's continue implementing our
JWT authontication filter
now we can go back to our filter
and finish the implementation
alright
so here we have our user details or we have our user
and the next step
is to validate
and check if the token is still valid or not
so here I will add if
JWT service dot is token valid
okay
and here I need to pass my JWT and the user details
that I just got from the database
alright so
if the token is valid
then what I need to do I need
like we have in here
we need if the user is valid
we need to update the security context and
send the request to our dispatcher circlet
alright so once the hour token is valid
I need to create an object of type
username password authonication token
so username password
authonication token
I will call it auth
token and this object is needed by
by spring and by the security context holder
in order to update our security context
okay so equals a new username and password
authentication token and it takes as parameter
the user details
and then for the next
parameter for the authorities I want
to pass it as null
and then the user details dot get authorities
so
here because we don't have credentials
as you remember when we created the user
we don't have credentials
so that's why I'm passing these credentials as
a null value
so
once
I finish creating or finish unstantiating this user
name authentication token
I want also to give it some more details
so I will use the oath token
set details and this details it takes an object
so I will pass a new object of type new
web authentication details source
fantication details source
and here I want to build the details out of our request
out of our HCTP request
alright now the final step is
as we mentioned here
the final step
is to update the security context holder
so to update the security context holder
its security context
holder get context
set authentication with our authentication token
alright and that's it
now let's
recap this one
so here when if we have our user email
and the user is not autonicated
we get the user details from the database
and then what we need to do
we check if the user is valid or not
if the user and the token is valid
so we create an object of type
username password authentication token
we pass user detains credentials and the authorities
as parameter and then we extend
or reinforce this authontication token
with the details of our request
and then we update the authontication token
and don't forget as a last step
and always do think about
after this if
think about always calling our filter chain
dot do filter
so we need always
to pass the hand to the next filters to be executed
okay and here we need the request and the response
and that's it about our JWT autonication filter
it is ready to use
let's move on and see what we need to implement next
this whole process is now implemented
but we still need to do some extra steps
the extra step we need to do is
to tell spring which configuration that we want to use
in order to make all this works
okay so we create the filter
we amplimatize that the user detailed service
validation updating context and so and so forth
but what we are missing is the binding
we need to bind
because we created a filter
but this filter is not yet used
so we need to use it
and in order to do that
we need to create a new configuration class
I will call it security configuration
okay so I recall this class security configuration
and this is going to be our
security configuration class
and as always to make a configuration class
become a configuration
we need to add this configuration annotation
from spring also
because we talk about security right here
we need to enable
web security let me make it for screen
and again we will need the required arcs constructor
so these 2 undertations they need to
they need to be
together when we when we work with spring boot 3.0
okay so
next what I what I will need to do
because as
at the startup or at the application startup
spring security will try to look for being off type
security filter chain
and this security filter chain is the bean
responsible of
configuring all the HCTP security of our application
so I will create a bean
public
security filter chain
I will call it security filter chain
and within this method of
this bean I will pass a parameter of type http security
I will call it just http
just for a short variable name
now let's start configuring our http security
so here as you can see
its type security filter chain
and to do that let's 1st return http build
and here we need to add also the exception
to the method segulature
because this build might throw an exception
alright so now to do the configuration
I will start by http
I will 1st disable the CSRF
verification and
we might talk about this in a different
video so here
now once we disable this one and now let's move on
or we will implement the configuration
the real configuration
so within the security
we can choose and decide what are
the urls and the pathes that we want to secure
but of course within
every application we have always a white list
white list means that we have some endpoints that
they do not require
any authentication or any tokens
that which are open for example
when we talk about
creating an account and logging
so in this case
to create an account we don't need a JWT token
because at that time we will create
user account and we will require or we'll ask for
a token after that also the same when we want to login
we don't need to pass the token as parameter
because we don't have one yet
so in this case
this is when we talk about white listing
and here is how we can implement white listing
so after disabling the CSRF
I want to authorize HCTP requests
and after authorizing
after using or calling this authorized HCP request
here we can call a request matcher
dot
request matchers
and for this request matchers we can pass a list
of strings and a list of patterns
this will represent
the application or our application patterns
we will go back to this later on
and for this list I want to permit all
I want all the requests in here all the
all this list I want to permit all
okay and then any request
all the other requests I want them to be authenticated
so this means I want to white list
this list and authorize all
the requests within this list
but any other request should be authenticated
okay now
let's talk about
and let's
see how we can configure our session management
the session management means what
we said that when we implemented the filter we want
a one spur request filter means
every request should be authenticated
this means that we should not
store the authonication state
or the session state should not be stored
so the the session should be stateless
and this will help us ensure that each
request should be authonicated
okay
so now we use the end to add a new configuration
and here let's add
dot
session management
and
here I want to talk about the session creation policy
how we want to create our session
so as I mentioned our session
we wanted to be stateless session
okay
so I will use session creation policy dot stateless
and like this
spring will create a new session for each request
and then end
here I need to tell spring
which authontication provider that I want to use
the authontication provider
I will explain it in just a few seconds
okay so I will just add it
authentication provider
and that will create an object of type
and then I will go back and create it later on
and then after the authontication provider
I want now to use the JWT filter that we just created
okay
so to do that I will use the method add filter before
because I want to execute this filter
before the filter
called username password authonication filter
because as you remember
when we implemented the JWT autonication filter
we check everything and then we set
security context we update the security context holder
and after that
we will be calling the username password authonication
filter okay
so here I will use
JWT off filter
I will call it like that
and I want it before the user name
password authentication filter dot class okay
now let's let me create this object
so I will use the
oops not local variable
but create a field
and this one I wanted to be of type JWT
authontication filter
okay
so this is the 1st one
and I needed to be final
so it will be automatically injected by spring
and the next one
is the authontication provider
so let s create a field
of type authentication provider and let s make it final
alright so now I have my configuration ready
all I need to do
or I need to implement now is this authentication
provider and let's do it right now
now we need to provide this authentication provider bin
so let's go to our application conflict class
and let's create a new bin
of type authentication provider
okay so for this authentication provider
let me make this full screen
so I want to create a bean
and always public
and the bean type authontication
provider
oh authontication provider
always from the spring framework package
and I will call it authontication provider
and let's start implementing this being right now
so
this authentication provider is the data access object
which is responsible to fetch the user details
and also include password and so and so forth
so for this we have
for this authentication provider
we have many implementations
and one of them is the dao
authontication provider
so data access object authentication provider
I will call it auth provider
equals new dao authontication provider
okay
so
within this authentication provider we need to specify
few properties
or like not few but just 2 of them
and the 1st one
is the user detailed service
so we need to tell this authontication provider
which user detailed service to use
in order to fetch information about our user
because we might have
multiple implementations of the user details
one for example
getting the information from the database
another one based
on a different profile
fetching the users
from in memory database from ELDAP and so and so forth
okay so for this one we already have our
oops we already have our user details
service right here
so this one is referencing this method
next we need to provide a password on encoder
so which
password encoder we are using within our application
so if you have a specific one
or if you are using a specific one
you need also to precise this one
because when we want to try
or we want to authenticate a user
we need to know which password
in order to be able to decode the password
using the correct algorithm
okay so earth provider dot
set password encoder and here I will create a method
I will call it password encoder
okay and I will create being out of it later on
so this is
the minimum required information that we need to
provide
and then all I need to do is returning this earth
provider right here
now I will just go ahead and create this
password encoder
so this password encoder is also should be also a bean
so it will be public and they will give it
the bean annotation
and for this I just need to return a new
B crypt password encoder
and that's it
so now I have my authontication provider
and also I created the password encoder being
one more step is needed to finish this application
config class which is the authontication manager
and the authontication manager
as the name indicates
is the one responsible to manage the authontication
so the authontication manager
have or has a bunch of methods and one of them
the reason method that
allow us or help us to authenticate
user based or using just the username and password
and for that we need
also to create a bean or to provide the bean to be
able to use it later on
okay so I will create a bean and public
authontication manager
because this is the bean that I want to create
and I will call it authontication manager
and within this bean I want to inject
an object of type authontication configuration
okay and I will call it config
this authontication configuration
hold already
the information about the authontication managers
so I will just return
config dot get authontication manager
right so here we are using the
default implementation of spring boot
and this is more than sufficient for us here
don't forget also to add
the exception to the method signature
so that's it let's move on and
now we're done with all the security configuration
for our application
but we still need
to provide at least 2 endpoints where the user
can create an account or
also can authenticate
and to do so within the BS package I will create
a package I will call it off
and within this package I will create a new controller
authontication
controller
and this authonication controller will have 2 endpoints
that will allow me to create
or register a new account
and authonicate an existing user
so in order to call this or to make this
class a controller
we need this annotation rest controller
and also I will give it a request mapping
and for the request mapping it will be slash API slash
we want slash off
and also I will need
the required arcs constructor
okay
now within this authontication controller
I will create 2 and points
one for register
and the other one for the authonticate
so the 1st one it will be a post mapping
and I will give it a register
for the name and here it will be a public
response
NTT and now the type will be authontication response
I will create an object later on for that
we will call this method resistor
and this register will need a request body
and this request body I will create an object called
register request
which will hold
all the
requests or the registration information like 1st name
last name email and password
okay
so I will leave it empty for now
we will implement it later on
I will do the same I will just copy paste this one
and I will create another method
but this one will call it authonticate
and it will also return an authontication response
but instead of register request
we will need an authontication request okay
so it's a northonication request
yep that's it
so we have our controller ready
now let's move on and start implementing things
let's now create our authentication response
so now just
amu I will use antility
to create this class authentication response
and we created within the same package
so this response is a simple class
that will have only a string token
so this is the token that would be sent back to the
to the customer or to the user
and to do that we will need the state annotation
we'll need the builder
and of course the all arcs constructor and the
no arcs
so that's it so our authontication response is ready
let's move on and create the register request
now let's create this register request class
so create a class right here
and we'll create it within the same package
so this registered request
it will also have few attributes like private
string 1st name
private string
last name and also an email and password
so we will also need the same annotations as
we used within this
authontication response
so just go ahead and copy them
and put them within this register request
okay
so now we have also our object register request ready
I will create as a next step
the authontication request object
finally we need to create this
automatication request within the same package
so I will just paste the same annotations
and here this object will hold
only 2 information which is the string email and
string password
okay so that's it our object now ready
let's move on and start implementing this
author register and
authenticate request
so for the
resistoration and authontication implementation
I will delegate this to a service
so within this author package I will create a new class
and I will call it authontication service
alright
this is the place or the class where I will implement
these 2 methods register and authenticate
so here I will just give it the service a notation
and of course the required arx constructor
alright so here we have these 2 methods
I will just move on
and here just make a simple call for
for these service methods but 1st let's inject it
okay so I will need private final authontication
service I recorded just service right here
and within this authontication service
let me make this full screen
now I will just
make the return statements for these 2 methods
alright so here I will return a response NTT
dot okay and I will call my service dot
register and I will pass this request as parameter
okay
and I will copy paste this
and paste it right here
and instead of resistor it will be authonticate
so here we don't have yet
our resistor and authonticate method
so let's go ahead and create them
so create method resistor
and this one will return the authontication response
so this is what we want to return
and now we can also create this authonticate method
and the same it should return an authontication
response
alright so now I will start implementing these methods
so now let's implement this register method
and this register will allow us to create a user
safe to the database
and return the generated token out of it
so for that because we need our
we want to interact with a database and save the user
so the 1st thing that we need is to inject our
repository
let's call it repository right here
and then what we need to do
I want to create a user
object out of this register request
so I will create our user equals user dot builder
and here dot build
so to build this user out of this register request
so I will have the 1st name which is
request dot get 1st name
same for the last name
and same for email
so it's email
and then the value will be the request to get email
now for the password
as you remember
we created our being of Thai password encoder
so for this we need to encode
our password before saving it to the database
okay so in order to encode the password we need
1st of all to inject
our password encoder service
so I will do that
password encoder password encoder
and this
I will use it right here password encoder dot in code
and here I have the get password or the request
dot get password
that we will receive within the registration request
okay so
here I will just make
a static roll always
so I will use a user roll
and then we call the building method
all right
so once we build our user object
the next step we need to do is our repository dot save
and we want to save the user that we just created
alright and finally
to be to return this authentication response
that contains the token
I will create a new variable I will call it JWT token
equals
now I will need my JWT service to generate that token
so I will I will inject also the private
final JWT service
and I will use it to create or to generate the token
using this user object right here
so JWT
service dot generate token
the one only using a user details for the moment
I don't need to set any extra claims
so
I will use this user
object to create or to generate a token
and finally
I will return an object of type authentication response
dot builder dot build
and I need to pass dot
token or I need to pass the token that I just generated
okay so this is the register method
and now everything is implemented
let's move on and implement this authenticate
for the authentication
it's it's an easy PC
so you remember we spoke before
about the authentication manager being
and we said that this authentication manager being
has a method called authonticate
which allow us to authonticate user
based on the username and password
so for that I will inject
1st of all my private final authontication manager
bean I will call it authontication manager
alright
so I will go back here to this authonticate method
and to authonticate the user
all I need to do is to call the authontication manager
orthonticate
and this authontication manager takes an object of type
username password authontication token
so I will pass a new
and within this I need to pass the email
so request dot get
email and also the password
request dot get password and
this authentication manager will do all the job for me
and in case the user is not
a username or the password are not correct
so an exception would be thrown
alright
so I'm totally secure when I just call this method
otherwise what I need to do
I need to create a user and if the user
so if I 1st of all if I get to this point right here
means the user is authenticated
so means the username and password are correct
if both of them are correct
so I will just need to generate a token
and send it back
okay so I will 1st of all find try to get the user
and find by email
and I will use the request dot get email
and here or else I will just throw
okay or just throw any exception
like it's not so important at this level
but for you
you might want to throw the correct exception
and you need to catch it
handle the exceptions and so and so forth
alright so
now I will just go ahead and copy
this code because it would be the same
and put it right here
so once I get the user
I will generate a token using this user object
and then return this
authonication response
so now we have this authonicate method and
the register method
ready to use
let's move on and see what is the next step
now we have our authentication controller ready to use
but there is one extra step that we need to do
do you remember when we 1st implemented
the security configuration and we spoke
about this white list right here
so what we need to provide now
within these request matches that we want to permit
all we need to provide or authorize
all the urls or all the methods
that we have within this authontication controller
so go ahead copy the request mapping that you created
and
for example here I want to authorize all the methods
that I have within this authentication controller
why because based on my design
everything that I have in here only
authentication related methods
so I don't have any business logic
methods or endpoints within
this authentication controller
so that's why I'm allowing I'm allowing
all the methods within this controller
so that's it
now let's create a demo controller for that
I will create a new controller within a new package
so right click here
new class and I will call the package demo
and I will call it demo
controller
so this demo controller will be also secured
so I want this endpoint to be secured
there will copy these annotations right here
paste it here and so
this one will be demo
and let's call a democontroller
and now
I will create just a get mapping a simple method
that
public that will return a simple string okay
response NTT
of type string
say hello for example
and then I will just return a response
NTT dot OK and with a body
hello from secured
hello from secret and point and that's it
now let's go ahead start our application and test
these changes
let's start the application and make sure
that all the code that we
wrote together is working fine
so go ahead click on start
and let's see what we would have in the console
so let's make sure that everything is fine
so as you can see here from the logs
we no longer have this autogenerated password
by spring security
and we have here that you are creating the sequence
and we have the table user gets created
and the application is running correctly
okay so now let's start our postman
and test this endpoint
so I have my postman started right now
so I will use this endpoint with then a get request
so the endpoint is local host and my port is 880
slash API slash B1 slash
demo controller is the same one that I have
right here within my code
it's democontroller
and now I will click on sand
we see that we have no authorization
we have nothing in here
so I will just go ahead and click on sand
and normally like the expected behavior
is this endpoint should be secured
okay so when I click on sand
we exactly can see that we have a 4 or 3 forbidden
means that we are not allowed to access this endpoint
okay
next we have our
2 endpoints the authonticate and the register
so let's 1st start with this register endpoint
or that's before that let's start with authonticate
and for the authonticate
now we know that we have no user within our database
we can also double check that
so if I open let me close
the other tabs so here I don't have any user resisted
within my database
okay but now if I try to connect
or to authenticate a non existing user
I also expect to have a 4 or 3 as a response
and this is what we see right here
so it's 4 3 forbidden
and the user is not allowed to access this endpoint
and this why because we have here within our schema
so we try to check and validate everything
even if the endpoint
even if the endpoint is secured
so we get into this authentication filter
we validate everything
but
once we get to the user details we don't have the user
in the database
so in that case we will send back a 403 to our customer
OK so now let's create a new user
so I will register a new user
so I give it alibu as the 1st name alibu last name
and alibu atmate com and 1234 as a password
so now when I click the send button
I should get a
generator token or a JWT token as a response
so this is what we see right here
so I will just copy this
token and I want to decode it
and let's see what we have within this token
so let's go back to the jwt.io website
and paste the generated token in here
so we
see that we have the algorithm here which is the HS256
the one we used to generate this token
and we have our payload
so we set already the subject
to the user email and we have the issue at
so the creation date and as you can see in here
it was created December 29
at 14 14 and this one will expire at in 24 hours
okay so
this is our generated token
let's go back and test the authontication right now
so we see that the register is working
but let's ensure that
within the same username and password we are also able
to get a token or to generate a token
so this is the same email and the password that we have
and if I click on sand I should get the token
but let's 1st
dry with a wrong password
so when they click on sand
so here we have our 44 or 3
and here it's because of this process
so we have the token
and then we start the validation process
so we extract the username and password
and then we are calling the user details
service to try to fetch the user from the database
and the user we got it because the user already exists
but when we move to the security filter chain
and to use when we move to security context holder
we will try also to use the authontication manager
to authonticate that user
using the password
and the user made that were provided
within the request
but this password is wrong
so that's why we are also throwing a 403 as a response
okay so now let's test with a correct password
so if I click on sand
I see that I have my JWT token
I will copy this one
and then I will go back to this
get method
I will click again and make sure that it's always 403
and how we can authorize
this request right now so within the authorization
here within the type click and choose beer token
alright
so remove or delete if you have something in here
and paste the token that you just
copy it okay now click on sand
and we see that we have the message
hello from secured endpoint
and we have this 200
OK which which is compatible with all this process
so we have the filter we validate
everything we check the token user details
and then we pass everything to security context holder
we updated and then
our request is sent to the dispatcher circulate
hit the controller and then we get our response back
so I hope
this was clear
if you have any questions
don't hesitate to drop a comment
and especially don't forget to follow me
to learn more and more about spring boots
oh key dokey congratulations
now you know how to implement JDBT using spring boot
3 which is the latest version of spring boot
and spring security as well
if you enjoyed this scratch course
literally just take one 2nd and smash that like button
also if you haven't subscribed to alibu channel
go ahead and subscribe
is go
awesome content around spring boot java and Angela
it was a pleasure
this is all for now and I'll catch you on the next one
I'll sell them while you go